# DIEGO LÓPEZ TAMAYO

# Mexico City

diego.lopez@colmex.mx

(+52) 5539526930  $\diamond$  LinkedIn: diegolopezt  $\diamond$  diego-eco.github.io

Economist with experience in sector analysis and forecasts for energy, financial, manufacturing, transportation, telecommunications and foreign trade. Focus on industrial organization, network economics, regulated sectors, economic competition and digital markets. Passionate about employing economic tools and data to promote development and reduce inequality in our society.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Senior Economist BBVA Reserach México

June 2021 - Present Day

Sectoral and regional analysis and forecasts for Mexico and the USA.

Big Data and Business Intelligence project management.

Consulting for business and risk departments.

Publications: www.bbvaresearch.com/author/diego-lopez

## International Business Research Groningen

March 2019 - September 2019

Local Consultant for IBR 2019 Mexico - University of Groningen.

Market study and analysis for the Mexican dairy sector.

www.ibr-groningen.nl

## Center for Economic Research on Innovation (CEPCyT)

January 2016 - July 2019

Research assistant for Dr. Leonel Corona Treviño.

Topics: economic innovation, entrepreneurship and economic theory.

www.cepcyt.org

## Contempo Publicidad

August 2015 - August 2019

Head of Digital Marketing. Graphic design and video editing for

digital marketing projects. Design of marketing campaigns on digital platforms.

#### **EDUCATION**

# El Colegio de México (Colmex)

 $August\ 2019\ \text{-}\ June\ 2021$ 

Master in Economics. Department of Economics CEE.

Thesis: Hedonic Pricing Analysis for Airbnb in Mexico City

#### University of Warwick, UK

January 2018 - July 2018

Academic exchange program.

Time Series, Industrial Organization and Labour Economics.

## Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México (UNAM)

August 2014 - June 2019

Bachelor in Economics (with honors).

Thesis: Ride-sharing platforms in Mexico City: Economic theory and empirical evidence.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# El Colegio de México (Colmex)

January 2023 - Present Day

Professor: Economic Networks. Graduated level. Department of Economics.

Theoretical models and application of network formation algorithms in Python

Financial Accounting. Bachelor's degree in economics. CFA Financial Statements Analysis

# Universidad de Guanajuato (Ugto)

May - June 2022

Course: Intermediate Python for Economists for professors of the Department of Economics and Finance. Scipy, Geopandas, Seaborn and NetworX applications

# El Colegio de México (Colmex)

August 2020 - December 2021

TA in Game Theory. Undergraduate level. Professor. Julen Berasaluce Iza.

TA in Microeconomics. Undergraduate level. Professor. Adriana Gama Velázquez.

## Faculty of Economics UNAM

January 2017 - December 2018

TA in Mathematics for Economics. Undergraduate level. Professor. Araceli Borja Rodriguez.

TA in Innovation and Technological Change. Undergraduate level. Professor. Leonel Corona Trevino.

#### RESEARCH

# Análisis de Precios Hedónicos para Airbnb en la CDMX

August 2021

El Colegio de México. Working Papers No. VII 2021

With Aurora A. Ramírez-Álvarez.

#### Efectos económicos, distributivos y ambientales

#### de la eliminación de las exoneraciones del IUSC en Costa Rica

December 2021

External consultor for the Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean (ECLAC) With Francisco Castillo Cerdas and Carlos A. López Morales.

# LANGUAGES AND SOFTWARE SKILLS

Languages Spanish (native). English (TOEFL iBT). French (DELF B2).

Modeling and Analysis R, Stata, Python, PySpark, SQL

Software & Tools MS Office, LATEX, Git, Adobe Suite, Google Data Studio, Power BI

Projects portfolio diego-eco.qithub.io/toolkit.html

#### Data Specialist Fundamentals

April - June 2022

Data Science Program. BBVA Campus

Exploratory data analysis with Python and SQL. Statistics and machine learning applications with Spark (PySpark environment) for Big Data

## Machine Learning: Feature Engineering

October - December 2021

Universidad Carlos III Madrid.

Boosting models, MSV, Multivariate analysis, dimensionality reduction.